Guide to the Propaganda Poster Collection 1914-1996
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
- Series 5: French Posters
  - Subseries 5.1: French World War II, 1939-1945
    - Les Prisonniers Rapatries du Canton de Remalard: vous Invitent a deux Representations "Comme au Camp", circa 1939-1945; French; 40 x 60 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: L'Emancipatrice (Folder 64, Item 356)
      Propaganda poster addressed toward the prisoners of Canton Remalard, announcing the presentation of "Comme au Camp.
    - Carte de l'Empire Francais: le Drapeau Francaise Flotte sur Toutes les Terres Colorees, circa 1940; French; 111.5 x 76 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 64, Item 357)
      Map of the world with areas highlighted in yellow, red, and blue, indicating the expansion of the French Empire. Includes three separate boxes color coded with the map, listing the names and kilometers of the countries and cities under French control.
    - Il Disait la Verite: ils l'ont tue!, circa 1944; French; 81 x 115 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 64, Item 358)
      Propaganda poster featuring a graphic of Philippe Henriot, a French politician and Minister in the French government.
    - Des Liberateurs?, 1944; French; 75 x 120 cm. Black, white, and red.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 64, Item 359)
      Propaganda poster depicting photographs of ten men, each with his name, nationality, and number of crimes listed below his image. Additional images featured below the ten men include train derailments, weapons, and wounded and dead men. Poster was displa
    - Affirmez Votre Volonte d'Obtenir: un Meilleur Ravitaillement, des Salaires Suffisants et de Remettre la France au Travail pour Gagner Vite a la Guerre, circa 1944-1945; French; 59.5 x 79 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 64, Item 360)
      A graphic of a man in front of industrial buildings with red smoky surroundings. Located in the lower right-hand side of the poster is a small image of a helmet detailed with a blue circle within a red circle. The back of the poster depicts a portion of
    - La France a Besoin d'une Jeunesse Robuste Garantie d'une Puissante Armee, 1945; French; 40 x 59.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 64, Item 361)
      Propaganda poster portraying an image of a young man throwing a discus while more young men and women playing tug-of-war in the background. Located in the lower right-hand side of the poster is a small image of a helmet detailed with a blue circle and a
    - Republicains, Antifascistes, Unissez-vous!., 1945; French; 40.5 x 59.5 cm. Color; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 65, Item 362)
      Propaganda poster illustrating the head of a female warrior (Marianne figure) in the foreground of a large crowd of people. Located in the upper left-hand side of the poster is a small image of a helmet detailed with a blue circle within a red circle. Th
    - La Jeunesse, Avenir du Pays Assuerera a la France des Lendemains qui Chantent., 1945; French; 39.5 x 59.6 cm. Color; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 65, Item 363)
      Propaganda poster depicting a graphic of nine young men and women, with the two in the foreground running on either side of the line of youths behind them. Located in the lower right-hand side of the poster is a small image of a helmet detailed with a bl
    - Contre toute Manipulation Monetaire Contre tout Blocage des Billets pour un Echange Valeur pour Valeur, 1945; French; 39.5 x 59.7 cm. Color; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 65, Item 364)
      French poster displaying an image of a hand holding a 100 currency note that is being cut in half by a pair of scissors. Located in the lower right-hand side of the poster is a small image of a helmet detailed with a blue circle and a red outer circle. T
    - Journee Nationale du Commerce, circa 1939-1945; French; 38.5 x 56 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Paris Chamber of Commerce. (Folder 65, Item 365)
      Features two sets of snakes, one red and the other blue, intertwining around a lit torch with wings on either side of the flame. The bottom middle portion of the poster contains a graphic of an early boat waving a red and blue flag. Main text is placed w
    - Un Million de Recompense: Avis a la Population, circa 1940; French; 44.5 x 55.5 cm.; Creator/Publisher: Prefecture of Police. (Folder 65, Item 366)
      Black and white. Poster broadcasting to the public a reward of one million francs.
    - Vous Avez la Clef des Camps: Travailleurs Francais vous Liberez les Prisonniers en Travaillant en Allemagne, circa 1939-1945; French; 38 x 55.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Bedos and Cie Imp. (Folder 65, Item 367)
      Propaganda poster portraying a hand holding up a single key that is illuminated in white against a blue background.
    - [Medical Examination], circa 1939-1950; French; 76.5 x 60.5 cm. Black, white, and blue.; Creator/Publisher: Beaux-Arts. (Folder 65, Item 368)
      Graphic of a doctor examining a young man with a stethoscope. Both figures are highlighted in white against a blue backdrop and medical equipment. Body of text is placed within a rectangle of a darker shade of blue.
    - Suivez-Moi. Gardez votre Confiance en la France Eternelle., circa 1940-1941; French; 81 x 120 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: E. Desfosses-Neogravure. (Folder 66, Item 369)
      Propaganda poster depicting a graphic of Philippe Petain in uniform and seated at a table.
    - [Racism and Anti-Semitism in Paris], circa 1939-1950; French; 100.5 x 65 cm. White background with red and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: International League against Racism and Anti-Semitism. (Folder 66, Item 370)
      Propaganda poster directed toward the people of Paris, warning them about the still current existence of the enemy, racism, and fascism.
    - Soiree Theatrale, circa 1939-1950; French; 40 x 60 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: L'Emancipatrice (Folder 66, Item 371)
      Directed toward all prisoners and the families of prisoners from d'Epinay-sur-Seine, inviting them to an evening theatre performance.
    - Representation, circa 1939-1950; French; 40 x 60 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: L'Emancipatrice (Folder 66, Item 372)
      Poster welcoming all returned prisoners and the women, children, and relatives of prisoners to a theatrical prisoner representation.
    - Representation, circa 1939-1945; French; 40 x 60 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: L'Emancipatrice (Folder 66, Item 373)
      Publicizing a performance for all returned prisoners of Neuilly-sure-Seine and their families.
    - Representation Theatrale, circa 1939-1950; French; 40 x 60 cm. Pink background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: L'Emancipatrice (Folder 66, Item 374)
      French war poster inviting all returned prisoners from Levallois and their families to a theatrical performance.
    - [German and French Notice], 1941; German; French; 108.5 x 73 cm. Red background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 66, Item 375)
      A public notice, written in both German and French, about the shooting of ten men. The ten names are organized in a numbered list.
    - [Patriotic French Figure], circa 1939-1945; French; 79 x 118.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: C.G.T. (Folder 66, Item 376)
      Propaganda poster portraying a patriotic male figure carrying a flag inscribed with C.G.T. and broken chains in the other hand against a yellow backdrop. Below him is a fallen soldier, a man dressed in all white with his arm raised, and an indistinct gro
    - Parisiens! l'Orgueilleuse Allemagne Hitlerienne vient de Capituler sans Conditions.., circa 1939-1945; French; 59.5 x 79 cm. Blue background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: The Committee of the Paris Liberation. (Folder 67, Item 377)
      Public announcement about the surrender of Nazi Germany.
    - Grand Gala et Bal de Nuit Avec Attractions: Organises par Ceux de la Resistance, 1945; French; 80 x 120 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: A. Karcher. (Folder 67, Item 378)
      Patriotic poster of a soldier and a woman dancing together. The woman's dress is decorated with red, blue, and white stripes, reflecting the colors of the man's uniform, the background, and the colors of the text.
    - Ouvrier! En Travaillant pour l'Europe tu Proteges ton Pays et ton Foyer, 1943; French; 80 x 119 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: ORAFF (Folder 67, Item 379)
      French, anti-communist propaganda poster depicting a worker gripping a hammer as he protects his wife and child from the Bolshevik bear.
    - Alerte! Au Cancer du Terrorisme Stalinien, circa 1941; French; 73.5 x 112.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: ORAFF (Folder 67, Item 380)
      Propaganda poster illustrating a siren in front of three stripes in the colors of the French flag. Below is a bloodlike splash of red behind the Soviet hammer and sickle.
    - Charlie Chaplin dans le Dictateur, circa 1940; French; 100 x 150 cm. Black and white with red accents.; Creator/Publisher: Aussel. (Folder 67, Item 381)
      " Promotional poster for Charlie Chaplin's "The Great Dictator. Features a drawing of Chaplin's head above a frenzied crowd of cartoon characters rushing toward three entryways.
    - Femmes, Lisez Ceci, circa 1939-1945; French; 108 x 159.5 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 67, Item 382)
      Propaganda poster directed toward French women, encouraging them to unite and perform their duty in order to end the war.
    - Exposition F.F.I: vers l'Armee Nouvelle, 1944; French; 100 x 150 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: E. A. Dauphin. (Folder 67, Item 383)
      Propaganda poster depicting two men dressed in brown and white wearing arm bands with the French colors. Behind them waves the French flag and they stand upon the words Exposition F.F.I which are designed to characterize mountains overlooking trees and b
    - Pour Gagner la Guerre...et Reconstruire la France Adherez au Front National, circa 1944-1945; French; 119 x 158 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Bedos and Cie. (Folder 68, Item 384)
      Poster portraying a graphic of a white, pink head looking upward toward three planes flying above, two green and one white. Upon the forehead of the face are three rings in the French colors placed within each other. Emerging from the top, right-hand sid
    - Gagner la Guerre, 1944; French; 118.5 x 160 cm. White background with red and blue text and accents.; Creator/Publisher: Bedos and Cie. (Folder 68, Item 385)
      Propaganda war poster announcing the First Congress of the National Front of the Isle of France. Includes a decorative border of red and blue bands.
    - l'Union de la Jeunesse Republicaine de France est nee, 1945; French; 120 x 160 cm. Pink, orange background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: The National Committee of the Youth Union of Republican France. (Folder 68, Item 386)
      Poster directed toward the youth of France to acquire individuals interested in the Republican Youth Union of France. Depicts drawings of two well-dressed, smiling youths, a man and a woman.
    - Soiree du Souvenir au Profit des Familles des Morts et Deportes de la Resistance P.T.T., 1945; French; 117 x 159 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: S. A. Courbet. (Folder 68, Item 387)
      Announcement of a remembrance event intended for the families of the deceased and deported men of the P.T.T. resistance. The majority of the poster is torn in half. Features numerous men performing various duties, all placed below a visual echo of the 'v
    - [German and French Notice from the Der Militarbefehlshaber], circa 1939-1945; German; French; 118.5 x 80 cm. Black and white with red accents.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 69, Item 388)
      A public notice, written in both German and French, announcing the provisions recalled to the public with the penalty against anyone who disobeys bolded and underlined. All of the text is surrounded by a red border and the notices are divided by two red
    - Les Socialism Contre le Bolchevisme: pour une Europe Libre, circa 1941-1944; French; 80 x 118 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: ORAFF. (Folder 69, Item 389)
      Propaganda poster representing the fight for freedom against Bolshevism through two cartoon figures in conflict. The man symbolizing freedom is wearing blue pants with a scene of green hills and a small house behind him, while he resists the chains of th
    - Stalingrad, Bucarest, Varsovie, Tannenberg, Elbing, Liegnitz: Quelques-uns des Eclatants Exploits de la Glorieuse Armee Rouge dont le 27th Anniversaire Marquera l'Etape Decisive de la Victoire sur l'Hitlerisme, 1945; French; 100 x 154 cm. White background with red and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 69, Item 390)
      Depicts an image of Joseph Stalin in the upper left-hand corner.
    - Youth Centres Feminins, circa 1941-1950; French; 120 x 160 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: ORAFF; General Secretary for Youth. (Folder 69, Item 391)
      Encourages the involvement of France's female youth. Poster portrays a large drawing of the head of a smiling young woman, flanked on either side by photographs of girls performing yard duties.
    - Banques et Compagnies d'Electricite ont Trahi! Exigez leur Nationalisation sans Indemnite, 1945; French; 60 x 80 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 69, Item 392)
      A collage of images of banks and electricity companies with gold highlights. Located in the lower right-hand side of the poster is a small image of a helmet detailed with a blue circle and a red outer circle. The back of the poster depicts a portion of a
    - Apres 4 ans d'Oppression...Fondons la Maison de l'Universite Francaise, circa 1945; French; 79.5 x 199 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Bedos and Cie Imp. (Folder 69, Item 393)
      Propaganda poster with a graphic of a white figure wearing a helmet decorated as a face and raising his fist that is clenched around a band of fabric striped with the French colors. Around his upheld wrist is a shackle attached to a broken chain and next
    - Theatre National de l'Odeon: Jeudi 1er Mars 1945 Grand Gala, French; 80 x 119.5 cm. White background with red and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Halles. (Folder 69, Item 394)
      Publicizing an event organized by the Association of Prisoners of War (sixth section) in the Theatre National de l'Odeon.
    - Apprendre un Metier un Bon Placement, 1943; French; 56 x 76 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: General Secretary for Youth. (Folder 70, Item 395)
      Propaganda poster encouraging youths to invest their time in the learning of a useful trade. Illustrates a young boy sitting on a crate, holding a hammer, as a he places his chin on his finger in a pondering state. Behind him are shadows of other young b
    - Eux Aussi: ont Droit a Notre Souvenir, 1943; French; 53.5 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Reunies-Lyon. (Folder 70, Item 396)
      Poster featuring an image of an open landscape with cross-shaped grave markers scattered in the background. In the foreground, are two grave markers with military helmets placed on top of them, and engraved with the years 1940 and 1939.
    - Commercants! Artisans!, 1945; French; 120 x 77.5 cm. White background with blue text.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 70, Item 397)
      Advertisement of a meeting held by the French Communist party directed toward French merchants and artisans.
    - [War Time Destruction], circa 1943; French; 80 x 105 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Crete-Corbeil. (Folder 70, Item 398)
      Propaganda poster with a graphic of a map of France against a black backdrop. Numerous cities are listed on the map, each one with a red flame painted to appear as if the city is burning.
    - Un Million de Tonnes de Charbon sont Accumulees sur les Carreaux des Mines du Nord et du Pas-de-Calais, circa 1939-1945; French; 79.5 x 119 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: L'Union des Syndicats Ouvriers de la R. P. (Folder 70, Item 399)
      Public announcement about an accumulation of one million tons of coal in Pas-de-Calais, France due to a lack of transportation.
    - 27e Anniversaire l'Armee Rouge: Hommage de la Nation Francaise Aux Armees Sovietioues, 1945; French; 78 x 115 cm. White background with red and blue text and accents.; Creator/Publisher: Curial-Archereau. (Folder 70, Item 400)
      Propaganda poster announcing a celebration of the 27th anniversary of the Red Army. Includes a graphic a red star at the top of the poster and a red and blue border.
    - Une Liberte en Peril, 1945; French; 76 x 110 cm. White background with blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Watelet-Arbelot. (Folder 70, Item 401)
      Encourages the French people to fight for freedom and liberty.
    - Sabotage de l'Effort de Guerre: les 3 Officiers de Maubeuge, 1945; French; 65 x 102 cm. White background with blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Committee for the Liberation Officers of Maubeuge. (Folder 71, Item 402)
      Poster explaining to the people of Paris, that three French officers, heroes of the Resistance, are being held in captivity for executing two traitors.
    - [Public Invitation to Liberation Event], circa 1939-1945; French; 65 x 107.5 cm. White background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: H. Dieval. (Folder 71, Item 403)
      Public invitation for an event held on June 1 by the municipality and the sixth committee of local release, discussing liberation. Includes two stripes, red and blue, in the upper left corner and the lower right corner.
    - Pour l'Ecrasement Definitif du Fascisme, le Chatiment des Traitres, l'Application du Programme du Conseil National de la Resistance: Commemoration des Fusilles de la Commune de Paris 27 Mai 1945 Manifestation au Mur des Federes, French; 85 x 120 cm. White background with brown text.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 71, Item 404)
      Propaganda poster featuring an event to commemorate the elimination of fascism and traitors in France.
    - Le Comite Parisien de la Liberation Organise salle de la Mutualite sous la Presidence de Louis Saillant un grand Rassemblement pour le Chatiment Immediat de Petain, des Traitres et des Criminels de Guerre, 1945; French; 76 x 112 cm. White background with blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Saint-Denis; Committee of the Liberation of Paris. (Folder 71, Item 405)
      Public notice of a rally held on May 31, 1945 arguing for the immediate punishment of Marshal Petain, traitors, and war criminals.
    - David Pourvoyeur de cet Immense Charnier doit etre Juge et Execute Immediatement: Nos Morts Crient Justice!, circa 1945-1949; French; 100 x 154 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Gaillard. (Folder 71, Item 406)
      Propaganda poster featuring the word "Ivry" in dripping blood red letters above a graphic of a man's face, holding up bloodied hands, as he views countless grave markers striped in red and blue. Presented by the National Association of Friends of Snipers
    - Hommage a Marcel Prenant, circa 1939-1950; French; 78.5 x 55.5 cm. White background with red and brown text.; Creator/Publisher: Sauvard. (Folder 71, Item 407)
      A tribute held by the National Council of Resistance, the French Union University, the Association of Friends of F.T.P.F., and the National Union of Intellectuals. Includes the date, time, and location in a bordered box in the upper left-hand corner.
    - Les Pays Changent: Katyn... Vinnitza... Hte Savoie.., 1944; French; 119 x 80 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 71, Item 408)
      Portrays a map of Europe with a photograph placed over France depicting people observing the deceased. Three red arrows point from the city names listed to the left of the map, to their locations. A Soviet Union flag protrudes from Europe, its shadow fal
    - Chaque Heure de Travail en Allemagne c'est une pierre Apportee au Rempart qui Protege la France, 1944; French; 78.5 x 118.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 72, Item 409)
      Propaganda poster featuring a graphic of a man laboring to place a white stone in a wall that is protecting from the flames on the other side.
    - Secreetariat General de la Jeunesse. Service de la Propagande: Centres de Jeunesse, circa 1941; French; 80 x 120 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: J. E. Goossens. (Folder 72, Item 410)
      Directed toward the youth of France. Features a graphic of two men in white shorts leaping into the air after a ball, with a large shovel pushed into the earth in the foreground.
    - Voici des Points Textiles: contre Chiffons Vieux Vetements et tous Dechets Textiles, circa 1944; French; 76.5 x 118.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Joseph-Charles. (Folder 72, Item 411)
      Poster featuring an illustration of articles of clothing in the shape they would take if worn by a person for the purpose of announcing the recovery of textiles.
    - Les Assassins Reviennent Toujours sur les Lieux de Leur Crime, 1944; French; 79.5 x 118 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: ORAFF. (Folder 72, Item 412)
      An anti-British propaganda poster depicting Joan of Arc, her wrists bound in chains, above a burning city. The backdrop is red with a series of black clouds, while the city is lit up with yellow and orange flames.
    - En Travaillant en Allemagne tu seras l'Ambassadeur de la Qualite Francaise, 1943; French; 37.5 x 55.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: ORAFF; Eric Castel. (Folder 72, Item 413)
      Propaganda poster encouraging French men to dedicate their time to working in Germany. Portrays a worker with an anvil and toothed wheel in front of the silhouette of the Eiffel Tower and a factory.
    - Bon Voyage!: Mais n'Oublie pas que j'Attends ton Retour pour Partis, 1943; French; 39.5 x 59.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: ORAFF. (Folder 72, Item 414)
      Poster featuring two men shaking hands, one wears clothes intended for labor work and the other is in a suit, with a train in the background. In the bottom right corner is a symbol of a labrys surrounded by the words Information de l'Etat Francais.
    - l'Aventure Francaise, 1942; French; 54.5 x 43 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: General Secretary for Youth. (Folder 72, Item 415)
      Illustrates a map of the world with France located at the center. Graphics of men, women, ships, animals, flags, etc. are placed on the map, paired with the year and a brief description of the event.
  - Subseries 5.2: French Post-World War II, 1943-1955
    - Concours en vue du Recrutement de Secretaires de Police Stagiaires et d'Inspecteurs de Surete Stagiaires, 1943; French; 44.5 x 56 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: La Gutenberg. (Folder 72, Item 416)
      Announcement of a competition to recruit police secretaries.
    - Toi Qui as le Bonheur d'Etre en Permission. Toi Qui as eu la Joie de Revoir ta Famille. Toi Qui n'Oublies pas ton Camarade, Repars pour qu'il Vienne a son Tour., circa 1943; French; 40 x 60 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: ORAFF. (Folder 72, Item 417)
      Poster illustrating a man along the right side, smiling and wearing a blue shirt and cap. In the bottom middle portion is a symbol of a labrys surrounded by the words Information de l'Etat Francais.
    - Grande Kermesse Nautique, circa 1941-1955; French; 62 x 95.5 cm. Green background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: ORAFF. (Folder 73, Item 418)
      Announcement of a grand event intended to assist the prisoners of war from Juvisy, Viry, and Draveil, France. The lower portion of the poster consists of a graphic of two men participating in water skiing.
    - Meeting de la Jeunesse Intellectuelle, 1945; French; 61 x 85. Blue background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Friends of "Present Time." (Folder 73, Item 419)